Guide to the Edward Curtis Dahl Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Edward Curtis Dahl Papers
1939-1986
RG 169
Yale University Divinity School Library
13
(32 boxes)
The E.C. Dahl Papers provided documentation of the life and work of a YDS graduate who was a Congregational minister. They contain correspondence, biographical materials, sermons, publications, and pastoral materials. Edward C. Dahl was ordained by the Congregational Church in 1941, and served churches in Massachusetts, Vermont, Connecticut, Wisconsin, New York, and New Hampshire. He authored numerous articles and sermons in various ministry publications, including Pulpit, Pulpit Digest, Church Educator and Advance. He died in 1993, survived by his wife, daughter Mary and sons Christopher and Edward.
Dahl, Edward Curtis, 1916-1993
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Chistopher and Edward Dahl Families, and Mary Dahl.
Biographical / Historical
Edward Curtis Dahl, son of Professor George Dahl and Elizabeth Curtis Dahl was born in New Haven, CT on April 5, 1916. His father was professor of Old Testament at the Yale Divinity School. E.C. Dahl attended schools in New Haven, and then Harvard College, graduating Magna cum laude and Phi Beta Kappa in 1938. He attended Union Theological Seminary and Yale Divinity School, graduating Magna cum laude from the latter in 1941.
Prior to graduation from YDS, Edward Dahl served during the summers of 1939 and 1940 as a student pastor in Eden Mills, VT, a resort community near the Canadian border. Correspondence and photographs suggest this was an especially pleasant and memorable period of time for young Dahl. Following graduation from Yale Divinity School, he spent the summer of 1941 in postgraduate study at both Union Theological Seminary and Mansfield College in England.
Upon his return, he chose pastoral ministry over the academy, accepted a call to Trinitarian Congregational Church in East Northfield, Mass., and was ordained in October of 1941. He spent the next three years in service to that congregation, and in 1944 accepted a call to Centre Congregational Church in Bratteleboro, VT. This position was followed in 1952 by a call to the First Church of Christ, Congregational, New Britain, CT. In 1962, Dahl accepted a position at the Fist Congregational Church of Appleton, WI, and in 1967 to the Garden City Community Church, Garden City, NY. Finally, in 1972, Dahl accepted a call to the Union Congregational Church of Petersborough, NH, where he served until his retirement in 1980.
During the course of nearly forty years of Congregational ministry, Edward Dahl also published extensively in devotional and ministerial publications, including numerous meditations for Church Educator, and a particularly well-received thirteen installment series on "The Christian Funeral" for Pulpit Digest. He also served on numerous local, state and national committees and boards within the Congregational (UCC) Church, and as President of the Yale Divinity School Alumini Association from 1965-67.
Scope and Contents
The Edward Curtis Dahl papers consist of 13 linear feet of material divided into 6 series:
Correspondence in Series I pertains to personal, academic and professional matters, and extends from 1937 through 1986. It includes letters of a personal nature from Amos WIlder and Arthur Schlesinger, Jr., and a great deal of correspondence pertaining to Dahl's career. Biographical materials in Series II include numerous newspaper clippings related to Dahl's career transitions, early photos from Eden Mills, VT, and obituaries and eulogies.
The bulk of the collection consists of hundreds of sermons are arranged in two subseries, chronological from 1939 to 1984, and a topical series, presumably arranged by Dahl himself, and generally arranged alphabetically. These subseries variously include notes for sermons, working drafts and "pulpit copies." This is a substantial collection covering a long era, and would seem to have historical significance, given its range and depth.
The publications of Series IV consist of drafts, manuscripts, and copies of Dahl's contributions to the ministerial and devotional press, including extensive devotions, and in particular a thirteen part series for Pulpit Digest concerning the Christian funeral. Dahl was also an ongoing contributor of meditations to Church Educator. Although this collection does not contain copies or drafts, save one, Dahl also had several sermons published in Pulpit.
Pastoral materials in Series V include various folders of notes and miscellany on given themes (humor, Bible study, etc.), and extensive prayer and quotation files, from which Dahl apparently drew when developing sermons, devotions, etc.. In addition, annual minister's reports, dated intermittently from 1939 through 1980, contain a plethora of detailed information regarding everyday Congregational ministry during those decades. Finally, personal materials include a limited amount of matter pertaining to extra-professional and alumni associations
These papers may be of considerable interest to students of Congregational pastoral ministry from the 1940's through the 1970's, or to historians concerned with religious life in the mid-twentieth century. The collection offers an abundance of detailed documentation of an extensive and very accomplished career in parish ministry in New England and elsewhere.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1939-1986, n.d.
II.Biographical Materials
III. Sermons, 1939-1980
IV. Publications
V. Pastoral Materials
VI. Personal Materials
Congregational churches -- United States; Clergy; Dahl, Edward Curtis, 1916-1993; Yale University. Divinity School
- Correspondence, 1939-1986, n.d.; Series I
  - Correspondence, including from Arthur Schlesinger, Jr., and Amos Wilder, 1939-1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1944-1986, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2-5)
- Biographical Materials, Series II
  - Photographs (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Obituaries, eulogy (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Sermons, 1939-1980; Series III
  - General
    - Sermons, list of titles, 1972-1980 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Sermons, Chronological, 1939-1984
    - Eden Mills, VT, 1939-1940 (Box 2, Folder 10-13)
    - East Northfield, MA, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
    - East Northfield, MA, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 17-22)
    - Brattleboro, VT, 1947-1959 (Box 4, Folder 23-28)
    - Brattleboro, VT, 1959-1962 (Box 5, Folder 29-34)
    - Brattleboro, VT, 1963-1965 (Box 6, Folder 35-39)
    - Brattleboro, VT, 1965-1968 (Box 7, Folder 40-45)
    - Brattleboro, VT, 1968-1971 (Box 8, Folder 46-51)
    - Brattleboro, VT, 1971-1973 (Box 9, Folder 52-57)
    - Brattleboro, VT, 1973-1975 (Box 10, Folder 58-63)
    - Brattleboro, VT, 1975-1977 (Box 11, Folder 64-69)
    - Brattleboro, VT, 1978-1984 (Box 12, Folder 70-76)
  - Sermons, Topical
    - Lenten, 1949-1957 (Box 13, Folder 77-81)
    - Lenten, 1958-1964 (Box 14, Folder 82-86)
    - Lenten, 1966-1974 (Box 15, Folder 87-89)
    - AA, Advent (Box 15, Folder 90)
    - Apostles, Ash Wednesday (Box 15, Folder 91)
    - Basic Christianity (Box 15, Folder 92)
    - Basic Christianity (Box 16, Folder 93)
    - Bible Sunday (Box 16, Folder 94)
    - Bible Sunday, Brotherhood (Box 16, Folder 95)
    - Christian Attributes (Box 16, Folder 96)
    - Christian Education, Christian Life (Box 16, Folder 97)
    - Christmas (Box 16, Folder 98)
    - Christmas (Box 17, Folder 99)
    - Christmas (Box 17, Folder 100)
    - Church Ministry (Box 17, Folder 101-102)
    - Church School, Church Union, Communion (Box 17, Folder 103)
    - Congregationalism, Conversion (Box 18, Folder 104)
    - Easter (Box 18, Folder 105)
    - Everymember canvass (Box 18, Folder 106-107)
    - Evil, problem of (Box 18, Folder 108)
    - Faith (Box 19, Folder 109)
    - Faith, family (Box 19, Folder 110)
    - Fellowship, God (Box 19, Folder 111)
    - God (Box 19, Folder 112-114)
    - God, Good Friday (Box 20, Folder 115)
    - Health, Hope (Box 20, Folder 116)
    - Immortality (Box 20, Folder 117)
    - Installation, Jesus (Box 20, Folder 118)
    - Jesus (Box 20, Folder 119-120)
    - Labor, Learning to See, Love (Box 21, Folder 121)
    - Man, Maundy, Memorial Day, Membership (Box 21, Folder 122)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 21, Folder 123)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 21, Folder 124-125)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 22, Folder 126-128)
    - Missions, Mother's Day (Box 22, Folder 129)
    - New Year's Day (Box 22, Folder 130)
    - Palm Sunday, Peace (Box 23, Folder 131)
    - Pentecost, Personal Religion (Box 23, Folder 132)
    - Prayer (Box 23, Folder 133)
    - Protestantism (Box 23, Folder 134)
    - Radio Broadcasts (Box 23, Folder 135)
    - Religion Christianity (Box 24, Folder 136)
    - Religion Christianity (Box 24, Folder 137)
    - Salvation, Scouting, Social Action (Box 24, Folder 138)
    - The Beatitudes (Box 24, Folder 139)
    - The Parables (Box 24, Folder 140)
    - The Parables (Box 25, Folder 141)
    - Thanksgiving (Box 25, Folder 142)
    - World Service, Worldwide Communion (Box 25, Folder 143)
- Publications, Series IV
  - Articles entitled "The Christian Funeral" ( Pulpit Digest ) (Box 25, Folder 144)
  - Correspondence in re "The Christian Funeral"; sermon; devotionals (Box 25, Folder 145)
  - Devotionals in Church Educator, "Educator's Meditations" (Box 26, Folder 146)
- Pastoral Materials, Series V
  - Annual minister's reports (Box 26, Folder 147-151)
  - Church governance (Box 27, Folder 152)
  - Church governance, by-laws (Box 27, Folder 153)
  - Funerals, eulogies (Box 27, Folder 154-155)
  - Marriages (Box 27, Folder 156)
  - Stewardship, children's ministry (Box 28, Folder 157)
  - Humor (Box 28, Folder 158)
  - Music, deacons (Box 28, Folder 159)
  - Bible study (Box 28, Folder 160)
  - Youth ministry (Box 28, Folder 161)
  - Christmas, Advent (Box 28, Folder 162)
  - reconfirmation, student ministry (Box 29, Folder 163)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 29, Folder 164-165)
  - Installation, ordination (Box 29, Folder 166-167)
  - Prayers, liturgy (Box 30, Folder 168-170)
  - Prayer, quotation files (Box 31, Folder 171)
- Personal Materials, Series VI
  - Alumni associations (Box 32, Folder 172)
  - Saturday Night Club (New Britain, CT) (Box 32, Folder 173)